I come from one of the most liberal,
أنا من أكثر بقعة متحررة،
tolerant, progressive places in the United States,
متسامحة، متقدمة في الولايات المتحدة،
Seattle, Washington.
سياتل، واشنطن.
And I grew up with a family of great Seattlites.
نشأت في أسرة عظيمة من سياتل.
My mother was an artist, my father was a college professor,
أمي كانت فنانة، أبي كان أستاذاً جامعيا.
and I am truly grateful for my upbringing,
وأنا ممتن لهم حقا على تربيتي،
because I always felt completely comfortable designing my life
لأنني شعرت دائما بالراحة الكاملة في تخطيط حياتي
exactly as I saw fit.
تماماً بالشكل الذي يناسبني.
And in point of fact,
في واقع الأمر،
I took a route that was not exactly what my parents had in mind.
فقد اتخذت مساراً غير ذاك الذي كان والدي يخططان له.
When I was 19, I dropped out of college --
عندما بلغت 19 سنة تركت الجامعة --
dropped out, kicked out, splitting hairs.
تركتها، طُردت منها، قولوا ما شئتم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I went on the road as a professional French horn player,
ثم اتخذت مساراً كمحترف في عزف البوق الفرنسي
which was my lifelong dream.
الذي كان حلم حياتي.
I played chamber music all over the United States and Europe,
عزفت الموسيقى المسرحية في جميع أرجاء أمريكا و أوروبا،
and I toured for a couple of years
وتجولت لسنوات قليلة
with a great jazz guitar player named Charlie Bird.
مع عازف غيتار الجاز العظيم تشارلي بيرد.
And by the end of my 20s,
وفي نهاية العشرينيات من عمري،
I wound up as a member of the Barcelona Symphony Orchestra in Spain.
صرتُ عضواً في أوركسترا برشلونة السيمفونية في إسبانيا.
What a great life.
ما أعظمها من حياة.
And you know, my parents never complained.
و لتعلموا فوالداي لم يشتكيا أبدا.
They supported me all the way through it.
بل دعماني خلال مساري.
It wasn't their dream.
لم يكن حلمهما.
They used to tell their neighbors and friends,
إعتادا إخبار جيرانهم و أصدقائهم،
"Our son, he's taking a gap decade."
"ابننا، في استراحة لمدة عقد."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And --
و--
There was, however, one awkward conversation about my lifestyle
ومع ذلك كانت هناك محادثة عويصة حول نمط حياتي
that I want to tell you about.
أود أن أخبركم بها.
I was 27, and I was home from Barcelona,
كنت في 27، وكنت عائدا إلى الوطن من برشلونة،
and I was visiting my parents for Christmas,
وقمت بزيارة والدي بمناسبة عيد الميلاد،
and I was cooking dinner with my mother, and we were alone in the kitchen.
و كنت أطبخ العشاء مع أمي وكنا لوحدنا بالمطبخ.
And she was quiet, too quiet.
وكانت هادئة، هادئة جدا.
Something was wrong.
كان هناك خطب ما.
And so I said, "Mom, what's on your mind?"
فقلت: "أمي مالذي يجول في ذهنك؟"
And she said, "Your dad and I are really worried about you."
فأجابتني: "أنا و والدك حقا قلقان بشأنك."
And I said, "What?" I mean, what could it be, at this point?
فقلت، "ماذا؟" أعني، ماهو الأمر، الآن؟
And she said, "I want you to be completely honest with me:
أجابتني: أريدك أن تكون صريحا تماما معي:
have you been voting for Republicans?"
هل كنت تُصوّت للجمهوريين؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, the truth is,
حسنا، الحقيقة هي،
I wasn't really political, I was just a French horn player.
أنني لم أكن سياسيا، كنت فقط عازف بوق فرنسي.
But I had a bit of an epiphany,
ولكن كنت مولعا بالاكتشافات،
and they had detected it, and it was causing some confusion.
وكانوا قد كشفوا ذلك، وسبب ذلك بعض الالتباس.
You see, I had become an enthusiast for capitalism,
كما ترون لقد كنت متحمسا للرأسمالية،
and I want to tell you why that is.
أريد ان أخبركم لم كان ذلك.
It stems from a lifelong interest of mine
يبدو أن ذلك من اهتمامي الدائم
in, believe it or not, poverty.
صدقوا ذلك أو لا، في الفقر.
See, when I was a kid growing up in Seattle,
كما ترون، عندما كنت صغيرا، ونشأت في سياتل،
I remember the first time I saw real poverty.
أتذكر أول مرة، رأيت فيها فقرا حقيقيا.
We were a lower middle class family, but that's of course not real poverty.
كنا عائلة من طبقة دون المتوسطة، ولكن ذلك بالطبع ليس فقرا حقيقيا.
That's not even close.
هذا ليس قريبا أبدا.
The first time I saw poverty, and poverty's face,
أول مرة رأيت الفقر، ووجه الفقر،
was when I was six or seven years old, early 1970s.
عندما كنت في السادسة أو السابعة من عمري، أوائل السبعينيات.
And it was like a lot of you, kind of a prosaic example, kind of trite.
وكان الأمر مثل الكثير منكم، مثالا غير منتظم، مبتذل.
It was a picture in the National Geographic Magazine
كانت صورة في المجلة الوطنية الجغرافية
of a kid who was my age in East Africa,
لطفل كان في عمري في شرق إفريقيا،
and there were flies on his face and a distended belly.
وكان هناك ذباب على وجهه وبطن منتفخ.
And he wasn't going to make it, and I knew that, and I was helpless.
ولم يكن لينجو من قدره المحتم، كنت مدركا لذلك ولكن لم أستطع فعل شيء.
Some of you remember that picture,
يتذكر بعضكم تلك الصورة،
not exactly that picture, one just like it.
ليس تلك الصورة بالضبط، ولكن أي صورة مثلها.
It introduced the West to grinding poverty around the world.
قدمت للغرب الفقر الحاد الموجود حول العالم.
Well, that vision kind of haunted me as I grew up and I went to school
حسنا، تلك الرؤية لاحقتني إلى أن كبرت وذهبت إلى المدرسة
and I dropped out and dropped in
وخرجت منها ورجعت إليها
and started my family.
وبدأت في تكوين عائلتي.
And I wondered, what happened to that kid?
وتساءلت، ما الذي حدث لذلك الطفل؟
Or to people just like him all over the world?
أو للأشخاص مثله الموجودين حول العالم؟
And so I started to study, even though I wasn't in college,
وبدأت الدراسة، بالرغم من أنني لم أكن في المدرسة،
I was looking for the answer:
كنت أبحث عن الإجابة:
what happened to the world's poorest people?
ما الذي حدث لأفقر الأشخاص في العالم؟
Has it gotten worse? Has it gotten better? What?
هل أصبحت حالتهم أسوأ ؟ هل تحسنت؟ أم ماذا؟
And I found the answer, and it changed my life,
ووجدت الإجابة، ولقد غيرت حياتي،
and I want to share it with you.
وأريد مشاركة ذلك معكم.
See --
كما ترون--
most Americans believe that poverty has gotten worse
يعتقد معظم الأمريكييون أن الفقر قد أصبح أسوأ مما كان عليه
since we were children, since they saw that vision.
منذ أن كنا أطفالا، بما أنهم شاهدوا تلك الرؤية.
If you ask Americans, "Has poverty gotten worse or better around the world?",
إن سألتم الأمريكيين، "هل أصبحت حالة الفقر حول العالم أسوأ أم أحسن؟"
70 percent will say that hunger has gotten worse since the early 1970s.
سيُجيب 70% من الأشخاص بأن حالات الجوع تفاقمت منذ أوائل سنة 1970.
But here's the truth.
ولكن هذه هي الحقيقة.
Here's the epiphany that I had that changed my thinking.
هذا هو الإكتشاف الذي غيّر تفكيري.
From 1970 until today,
منذ سنة 1970 إلى الآن،
the percentage of the world's population
إن نسبة سكان العالم
living in starvation levels,
التي تُعيش في مستويات الجوع،
living on a dollar a day or less, obviously adjusted for inflation,
تعيش على دولار أو أقل في اليوم، طبعا مع التعديل اللازم لحساب التضخم،
that percentage has declined
هذه النسبة انخفضت
by 80 percent.
بنسبة 80 بالمائة.
There's been an 80 percent decline in the world's worst poverty
كان هناك انخفاض بنسبة 80% لأسوأ حالات الفقر في العالم
since I was a kid.
منذ أن كنت طفلا.
And I didn't even know about it.
ولم أكن أعرف حتى بذلك.
This, my friends, that's a miracle.
هذا يا أصدقائي معجزة.
That's something we ought to celebrate.
هذا شيء ينبغي أن نحتفل به.
It's the greatest antipoverty achievement in the history of mankind,
إنه أعظم إنجاز ضد للفقر في تاريخ الإنسانية،
and it happened in our lifetimes.
وقد حدث في حياتنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So when I learned this, I asked, what did that? What made it possible?
وعندما عرفت ذلك، تساءلت ما الذي مكننا من القيام بذلك؟ وكيف أصبح ممكنا؟
Because if you don't know why, you can't do it again.
فإن لم تعرف لماذا؟ لن تستطيع القيام بذلك مرة أخرى.
If you want to replicate it
إذا أردت القيام بذلك مرة أخرى
and get the next two billion people out of poverty,
وإخراج ملياري شخص من الفقر،
because that's what we're talking about: since I was a kid,
فذلك ما كنا نتحدث عنه منذ أن كنت طفلا،
two billion of the least of these, our brothers and sisters,
على الأقل ملياري شخص من هؤلاء، إخواننا وأخواتنا،
have been pulled out of poverty.
تم إخراجهم من الفقر.
I want the next two billion, so I've got to know why.
أريد مليارين آخرين لذا أردت معرفة السبب.
And I went in search of an answer.
وبدأت في البحث عن الإجابة.
And it wasn't a political answer, because I didn't care.
ولم تكن إجابة سياسية، لانني لم أهتم.
You know what, I still don't care.
أتعرفون، مازلت لا أهتم.
I wanted the best answer from mainstream economists
أردت أفضل إجابة من قبل الإقتصاديين
left, right and center.
اليسار واليمين والمركز.
And here it is.
وها نحن.
Here are the reasons.
هذه هي الأسباب.
There are five reasons that two billion of our brothers and sisters
هذه 5 أسباب لأخراج مليارين من إخواننا وأخواتنا
have been pulled out of poverty since I was a kid.
من الفقر منذ أن كنت طفلا.
Number one: globalization.
أولا: العولمة.
Number two: free trade.
ثانيا: التجارة الحرة.
Number three: property rights.
ثالثا: حقوق الملكية.
Number four: rule of law.
رابعا: سيادة القانون.
Number five: entrepreneurship.
خامسا: خلق المشاريع.
It was the free enterprise system spreading around the world
لقد كان هذا بسبب نظام الاقتصاد الحر المنتشر حول العالم
after 1970 that did that.
بعد سنة 1970.
Now, I'm not naive.
حاليا، لست ساذجا.
I know that free enterprise isn't perfect,
أعرف أن المؤسسات الحرة ليست مثالية،
and I know that free enterprise isn't everything we need
أعلم أن المؤسسات الحرة ليست كل ما نحتاجه
to build a better world.
لبناء عالم أفضل.
But that is great.
ولكن هذا رائع.
And that's beyond politics.
وأبعد من السياسة.
Here's what I learned. This is the epiphany.
هذا ما تعلمته. هذا ما اكتشفته.
Capitalism is not just about accumulation.
الرأسمالية ليست التراكم فقط.
At its best, it's about aspiration,
لأنها في أفضل حالاتها، طموح،
which is what so many people on this stage talk about,
وهو ما يتحدث عنه الكثير من الأشخاص فوق هذه المنصة،
is the aspiration that comes from dreams
الطموح الذي يأتي من الأحلام
that are embedded in the free enterprise system.
وهي جزء لا يتجزأ من نظام الإقتصاد الحر.
And we've got to share it with more people.
وعلينا أن نتقاسمه مع عدد أكثر من الأشخاص.
Now, I want to tell you about a second epiphany
والآن، أريد أن أطلعكم على اكتشاف ثان
that's related to that first one
وهو مرتبط بالاكتشاف الأول
that I think can bring us progress, not just around the world,
والذي أعتقد أنه سيساهم في التطور ليس فقط حول العالم،
but right here at home.
وإنما هنا في الوطن.
The best quote I've ever heard
أفضل مقولة سمعتها
to summarize the thoughts that I've just given you
لتلخيص الأفكار التي قلتها لكم قبل قليل
about pulling people out of poverty
حول إخراج الأشخاص من الفقر
is as follows:
هي التالية:
"Free markets have created more wealth than any system in history.
"خلقت الأسواق الحرة مزيدا من الثروة أكثر من أي نظام في التاريخ.
They have lifted billions out of poverty."
لقد أخرجت مليارات الأشخاص من الفقر."
Who said it?
من قال هذا؟
It sounds like Milton Friedman or Ronald Reagan.
يبدو كأنه ميلتون فريدمان أو رونالد ريغان.
Wrong.
هذا خاطئ.
President Barack Obama said that.
الرئيس باراك أوباما هو من قال ذلك.
Why do I know it by heart?
لما أعرف ذلك عن ظهر قلب؟
Because he said it to me.
لأنه قال لي ذلك.
Crazy.
جنون.
And I said, "Hallelujah."
وقلت: "هاليلويا"
But more than that, I said,
ولكن أكثر من ذلك، قلت،
"What an opportunity."
"يا لها من فرصة"
You know what I was thinking?
أتعرفون ما كنت أفكر فيه؟
It was at an event that we were doing on the subject
كان ذلك أثناء حدث كنا نقوم به حول هذا الموضوع
at Georgetown University in May of 2015.
في جامعة جورج تاون في مايو 2015.
And I thought, this is the solution
وفكرت، أن هذا هو الحل
to the biggest problem facing America today. What?
للمشكلة الكبيرة التي تُواجهها أمريكا اليوم. ماذا؟
It's coming together around these ideas,
تتمحور حول هذه الأفكار،
liberals and conservatives,
الليبراليين والمحافظين،
to help people who need us the most.
لمساعدة الناس الذين هم في أمسّ الحاجة إلينا.
Now, I don't have to tell anybody in this room that we're in a crisis,
حاليا، لن أضطرّ لإخبار أي أحد في هذه القاعة بأننا في أزمة،
in America and many countries around the world with political polarization.
في أمريكا والعديد من البلدان حول العالم تتعلّق بالاستقطاب السياسي.
It's risen to critical, crisis levels.
وقد ارتفعت إلى مستويات الأزمة الحرجة.
It's unpleasant. It's not right.
هذا غير سارّ وليس صحيحا.
There was an article last year
كان هناك مقال في السنة الماضية
in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences,
في وقائع الأكاديمية الوطنية للعلوم،
which is one of the most prestigious scientific journals
وهي من أكثر الصحف المرموقة
published in the West.
التي تنشر في الغرب.
And it was an article in 2014
كان مقال قد نُشر في سنة 2014
on political motive asymmetry.
حول عدم تناسق التحرك السياسي.
What's that? That's what psychologists call the phenomenon
ما هذا؟ هذا ما يسميه أطباء علم النفس ظاهرة
of assuming that your ideology is based in love
افتراض أن عقيدتكم ترتكز على الحب
but your opponents' ideology is based in hate.
ولكن عقيدة خصمك ترتكز على الكراهية.
It's common in world conflict.
هذا شائع في النزاع العالمي.
You expect to see this between Palestinians and Israelis, for example.
من المتوقع رؤية هذا بين الفلسطنيين والإسرائليين، مثلا.
What the authors of this article found
ما وجده كتاب هذا المقال كان
was that in America today, a majority of Republicans and Democrats
في أمريكا اليوم، يُعاني معظم الجمهوريين والديمقراطيين
suffer from political motive asymmetry.
من عدم تناسق التحرك السياسي.
A majority of people in our country today who are politically active believe
أغلبية الأشخاص اليوم من الناشطين سياسيا في بلادنا يعتقدون
that they are motivated by love but the other side is motivated by hate.
بأنهم يتحركون بدافع الحب بينما دافع الجهة الأخرى هو الكره.
Think about it. Think about it.
فكّروا في هذا. فكّروا في هذا.
Most people are walking around saying,
معظم الناس يقولون:
"You know, my ideology is based on basic benevolence,
"كما تعرفون، ترتكز عقيدتي على التعاطف،
I want to help people,
أريد أن أساعد الناس،
but the other guys, they're evil and out to get me."
ولكن الأشخاص الآخرين أشرار وهم لي بالمرصاد."
You can't progress as a society when you have this kind of asymmetry.
لا يمكنكم التطور كمجتمع عندما تُعانون من هذا النوع من عدم التناسق.
It's impossible.
هذا مستحيل.
How do we solve it?
كيف نجد حلّا لهذا؟
Well, first, let's be honest: there are differences.
حسنا، أولا، لنكن صريحين: توجد اختلافات.
Let's not minimize the differences. That would be really naïve.
دعونا لا نقلل من شأن الاختلافات. هذا سيكون نوعا من السذاجة.
There's a lot of good research on this.
توجد عديد من البحوث الجيدة حول هذا الأمر.
A veteran of the TED stage is my friend Jonathan Haidt.
أحد مُحاضري TED القٌدامى هو صديقي جوناثان هايدت.
He's a psychology professor at New York University.
هو طبيب في علم النفس في جامعة نيويورك.
He does work on the ideology and values and morals of different people
يقوم بدراسات حول العقيدة والقيم والأخلاق لعدّة أشخاص
to see how they differ.
لاكتشاف كيفية اختلافهم.
And he's shown, for example, that conservatives and liberals
وقد أثبت مثلا أن المحافظين والليبراليين
have a very different emphasis on what they think is important.
لديهم أهميات مختلفة في ما يعتقدون أنها مهمة.
For example, Jon Haidt has shown
مثلا:، أثبت جون هايديت
that liberals care about poverty
أن الليبراليين يهتمون بالفقر
59 percent more than they care about economic liberty.
بنسبة 59 بالمائة أكثر من اهتمامهم بالحرية الاقتصادية.
And conservatives care about economic liberty
ويهتم المحافظون بالحرية الاقتصادية
28 percent more than they care about poverty.
بنسبة 28 بالمائة أكثر من اهتمامهم بالفقر.
Irreconcilable differences, right?
اختلافات متناقضة أليس كذلك؟
We'll never come together. Wrong.
ولن نتفق أبدا. خطأ.
That is diversity in which lies our strength.
هذا هو التنوّع الذي تكمن فيه قوتنا.
Remember what pulled up the poor.
تتذكرون ما الذي أخرج الفقراء من فقرهم.
It was the obsession with poverty,
كان ذلك الهوس بالفقر،
accompanied by the method of economic freedom
المرتبط بطريقة الحرية الاقتصادية
spreading around the world.
التي انتشرت حول العالم.
We need each other, in other words,
نحن في حاجة إلى بعضنا البعض، أو بمعنى آخر،
if we want to help people and get the next two billion people out of poverty.
إذا أردنا مساعدة الأشخاص وإخراج ملياري شخص آخرين من الفقر.
There's no other way.
لا توجد طريقة أخرى.
Hmm.
همممم.
How are we going to get that?
كيف سنقوم بذلك؟
It's a tricky thing, isn't it.
إنه شيء محيّر، أليس كذلك؟
We need innovative thinking.
نحن في حاجة إلى تفكير خلّاق.
A lot of it's on this stage.
الكثير منه على هذه المنصة.
Social entrepreneurship. Yeah. Absolutely. Phenomenal.
خلق مشاريع اجتماعية نعم. بالطبع. متميزة.
We need investment overseas
نحتاج إلى الاستثمار وراء البحار
in a sustainable, responsible, ethical and moral way. Yes. Yes.
بطريقة مستدامة وأخلاقية ومسؤولة. نعم .نعم.
But you know what we really need?
ولكن هل تعرفون ما نحتاجه حقا؟
We need a new day in flexible ideology.
نحتاج إلى يوم جديد بإيديولوجية مرنة.
We need to be less predictable.
ينبغي أن نكون أقل قابلية للتنبؤ بها.
Don't we?
أليس كذلك؟
Do you ever feel like your own ideology is starting to get predictable?
هل تشعر بأن عقيدتك بدأت تصبح قابلة للتنبؤ ؟
Kinda conventional?
تقليدية نوعا ما؟
Do you ever feel like you're always listening to people who agree with you?
هل تشعر بأنك تستمع دائما إلى أشخاص يتفقون معك؟
Why is that dangerous?
لماذا يكون هذا خطيرا؟
Because when we talk in this country about economics,
لأننا عندما نتحدث في هذا البلد حول الاقتصاديات،
on the right, conservatives,
على اليمبن، المحافظين،
you're always talking about taxes and regulations and big government.
أنتم دائما تتحدثون عن الضرائب والقوانين والحكومة الكبيرة.
And on the left, liberals, you're talking about economics,
على اليسار، الليبرليون، أنتم تتحدثون عن الاقتصاديات،
it's always about income inequality.
يتمحور الأمر دائما حول عدم المساواة في الدخل.
Right? Now those are important things,
صحيح؟ هذه الأشياء مهمة الآن،
really important to me, really important to you.
مهمة جدا بالنسبة لي. مهمة جدا بالنسبة لكم.
But when it comes to lifting people up
ولكن عندما يتعلق الأمر بإنقاذ الأشخاص
who are starving and need us today, those are distractions.
الذين يتضورون جوعا وهم في حاجة إلينا، هذه ستصرف الانتباه عنها.
We need to come together around the best ways
نحن في حاجة إلى الاتحاد معا والاتفاق على أحسن الطرق
to mitigate poverty using the best tools at our disposal,
للتخفيف من الفقر باستعمال أفضل الوسائل التي في حوزتنا،
and that comes only when conservatives recognize that they need liberals
ويمكن تحقيق ذلك عندما يعترف المحافظون بحاجتهم إلى الليبراليون
and their obsession with poverty,
وهوسهم بالفقر،
and liberals need conservatives and their obsession with free markets.
وبحاجة الليبيراليون إلى المحافظون وهوسهم بالتجارة الحرة.
That's the diversity in which lies the future strength of this country,
هذه هو التنوع حيث تكمن القوة المستقبلية لهذه البلاد،
if we choose to take it.
إذا اخترناها.
So how are we going to do it? How are we going to do it together?
لذا كيف سنقوم بذلك، كيف سنقوم بذلك معا؟
I've got to have some action items, not just for you but for me.
لقد حصلت على بعض قواعد العمل، ليس لكم فقط، بل لي أيضا.
Number one. Action item number one:
أولا. قاعدة العمل الأولى:
remember, it's not good enough just to tolerate people who disagree.
تذكروا، ليس جيدا بما فيه الكفاية أن تتسامح مع من يختلف معك.
It's not good enough.
هذا ليس جيدا بما فيه الكفاية.
We have to remember that we need people who disagree with us,
يجب أن نتذكر أننا في حاجة إلى الأشخاص المختلفين معنا،
because there are people who need all of us
لأنه يوجد أشخاص في حاجة إلينا جميعا
who are still waiting for these tools.
مازالوا ينتظرون هذه الوسائل.
Now, what are you going to do? How are you going to express that?
الآن، ما الذي ستقومون به؟ و كيف ستعبرون عن ذلك؟
Where does this start? It starts here.
من أين يبدأ هذا؟ إنه يبدأ من هنا.
You know, all of us in this room, we're blessed.
أتعرفون، كلنا في هذه القاعة الآن مباركون.
We're blessed with people who listen to us.
نحن مباركون بالناس التي تسمعنا.
We're blessed with prosperity. We're blessed with leadership.
نحن مباركون بالرفاهة. نحن مباركون بالقيادة.
When people hear us, with the kind of unpredictable ideology,
عندما يسمعنا الآخرون، مع هذا النوع من الإيديولوجيا غير المتوقعة،
then maybe people will listen.
يُمكن أن يستمع الناس.
Maybe progress will start at that point.
ربما يُمكن التقدم في اتجاه تلك النقطة.
That's number one. Number two.
هذه الرقم واحد. الرقم إثنان .
Number two: I'm asking you and I'm asking me
الرقم أثنان: أنا أطلب منكم وأطلب من نفسي
to be the person specifically who blurs the lines,
أن نكون ذلك الشخص الذي يتجاوز الحواجز،
who is ambiguous, who is hard to classify.
الشخص الغامض، الذي يصعب تصنيفه.
If you're a conservative,
إن كنت شخصا مُحافظا،
be the conservative who is always going on about poverty
كن ذلك الشخص المحافظ الذي يسعى دائما حول الفقر
and the moral obligation to be a warrior for the poor.
والواجب الأخلاقي ليكون مُحاربا للفقر.
And if you're a liberal, be a liberal who is always talking
وإن كنت ليبراليا، كن ليبراليا ممن يتحدثون دائما
about the beauty of free markets to solve our problems
حول جمال الأسواق الحرة لمعالجة مشاكلنا
when we use them responsibly.
عند استخدامها بمسؤولية.
If we do that, we get two things.
إن قمنا بذلك، فسيكون لدينا شيئين.
Number one: we get to start to work on the next two billion
أولا: ينبغي أن نبدأ العمل على المليارين المقبلين
and be the solution that we've seen so much of in the past
وأن نكون الحل الذي رأيناه كثيرا في الماضي
and we need to see more of in the future. That's what we get.
ونحتاج لرؤية المزيد منه في المستقبل. هذا ما سيكون عليه الأمر.
And the second is that we might just be able
وثانيا، فإننا قد نكون قادرين
to take the ghastly holy war of ideology that we're suffering under in this country
على تغيير الحرب الإيديولوجية المقدسة الرهيبة التي نُعاني منها في هذا البلد
and turn it into a competition of ideas
وتحويلها إلى تنافس في الأفكار
based on solidarity and mutual respect.
أساسه التضامن والاحترام المتبادل.
And then maybe, just maybe,
وبعدها، ربما، فقط ربما،
we'll all realize that our big differences
سنعي بأن أكبر اختلافاتنا
aren't really that big after all.
ليست على هذا القدر من الاختلاف حقا.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)